Inventory of the William P. Miller papers
Hoover Institution Archives
William P. Miller papers
1939-1973
77074
Hoover Institution Archives
4 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize boxes, 15 envelopes, 5 motion picture film reels, memorabilia (3.3 linear feet)
Letter, biographical information, motion picture film, and photographs relating to United States Army Signal Corps operations in North Africa, Germany, Italy and France during World War II. Includes a Nazi flag. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Miller, William P., 1905-1973.
Access
Collection is open for research.
Use copies of all motion picture film in this collection are available for immediate access; digital copies also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1977.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternate Forms Available
Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Related Collection(s)
Dachau (Concentration camp) miscellaneous records, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical Note
William P. Miller served as a lieutenant colonel in command of the United States Army Signal Corps personnel division in the Sixth Army Group during World War II. He was deployed to North Africa, Italy, Corsica, France, and Germany and was awarded six Battle Stars, two Bronze Stars, the Legion of Merit, and Croix de Guerre with Palm.
Scope and Content of Collection
The William P. Miller papers consist of news clippings, a military order, printed matter, photographs, motion picture film, and a Nazi flag relating to Miller’s career with the Sixth Army Group of the United States Army Signal Corps. The collection mainly consists of the photographs and film reels, which depict United States operations in North Africa, Italy, France, and Germany during World War II. The collection also includes personal papers and printed matter from his civilian position in the insurance business.
United States. Army. Signal Corps.; World War, 1939-1945--Pictorial works.; Motion pictures.
- Biographical File, 1944-1973
  Scope and Contents note
  Consists of news clippings, military orders, telegrams, printed matter, an eulogy, and a Nazi flag relating to Miller’s military career and personal life.
  - Retirement book, 1970 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - General material, 1944-1973 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Item list of North African photographs [See Envelope G in Photographs], 1945 June (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Nazi flag, undated (Box 2)
- Motion Picture Film, circa 1943-1945
  Five unique amateur films, made from approximately 1943 to 1945, featuring footage of the North African and European theaters during World War II. Included are remote landscapes in Morocco seemingly untouched by war intercut with battle-scarred cities at the center of conflict. Shot on silent 16mm Kodachrome film.
  - Moulay Idriss, Khenifra, circa 1943 (Reel 1)
    Access
    Use copy available on-site for immediate use. Use copy reference number: 77074_f_0010696.
    16mm reversal original, silent, edited, color.
    Scenes of the Moroccan cities Moulay Idriss and Khenifra. Footage includes shots of local inhabitants; cityscapes; a remote village with thatched huts; and ancient ruins. The ruins are likely the remains of the Roman city Volubilis in Morocco. The ruins are also pictured among the unstamped photographs in the collection and identified as Volubilis in Miller’s list. Reel 1 also includes shots of US servicemen riding in jeeps in the Moroccan countryside and sharing tea with their hosts in what appears to be the home of a local Khenifra townsman.
  - Casablanca, Marrakech, Meknes, 1943 (Reel 2)
    Use copy available on-site for immediate use. Use copy reference number: 77074_f_0010692.
    Scenes of Casablanca, Marrakech, and Meknes. Footage includes shots of local villagers and townspeople both inside and outside of the city walls; flower gardens, homes, mosques, and other buildings; Moroccan soldiers marching in formation and riding on horseback; a group of children in tattered clothing huddled in a doorway in a city; a man in a fez hat posing for the camera just outside the city; a US serviceman walking on a busy city street alongside local townspeople; women in traditional attire with baskets on their heads on a village road; a Moroccan officer patrolling a city street; and a child among livestock at a watering hole.
  - Africa, Algeria, Corsica, St. Tropez, Toulon, 1944 (Reel 3)
    Use copy available on-site for immediate use. Use copy reference number: 77074_f_0010694.
    Scenes of Algiers, Corsica, and the port cities of Saint Tropez and Toulon in southern France. Footage includes battle ships in the Bay of Algiers and in the port of Saint Tropez; the Notre Dame d’Afrique (Our Lady of Africa), a Roman Catholic church built by French colonists in Algiers in 1872; a child and two adults on a cliff watching what appears to be a damaged warship in the Bay of Algiers; US servicemen in front of the Hotel Napoleon Bonaparte; a German minefield, most likely in France; a sign with skull and cross bones and the words "Achtung Minen" (Warning Mines) next to a field barricaded by barbed wire; and a downed aircraft in a field.
  - Germany, circa 1945 (Reel 4)
    Use copy available on-site for immediate use. Use copy reference number: 77074_f_0010687.
    Scenes of bombed cities in Germany. The cities featured are Ludwigshafen and Mannheim. Footage includes shots of military trucks driving through rubble-lined streets with rows of heavily damaged buildings; a collapsed railway bridge over the River Rhine between Mannheim and Ludwigshafen; a pontoon bridge with soldiers in the foreground and military trucks on the bridge heading into the city; and the damaged Rosengarten concert hall in Mannheim. The U.S. Corps of Engineers likely constructed the pontoon bridge to allow access to the city after the main bridge was compromised. Miller’s film features the damaged bridge before the Ernie Pyle Memorial Bridge was constructed in 1945.
  - Germany, Austria, 1945 (Reel 5)
    Use copy available on-site for immediate use. Use copy reference number: 77074_f_0010684.
    Scenes of Germany and Austria. Footage includes Adolf Hitler’s mountain home Berghof, in the Bavarian Alps near Berchtesgaden, Germany, with armed soldiers patrolling the grounds; U.S. servicemen gathered in a German town and walking along an overpass in the Alps; two destroyed bridges; and a sign for Brenner Pass.
- Photographs, 1939-1970
  Consists of images from North Africa, Italy, France, and Germany. The photographs mainly follow the final months of the war with the United States Army pushing through Eastern France and into Germany. There are prints and negatives of frontline battles, wreckage, and civilian life. Of particular note are prints of "Colmar Pocket," or Brückenkopf Elsaß, Allied liberation, and Dachau concentration camp.
  - 2 colleague portraits, undated (Box 3)
  - California Insurance Holding Company System Regulatory Act signing, including cartoon, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
  - Germany, Austria, France, primarily U.S. Signal Corps photos of German surrender, 1945 April-May (Envelope A-F)
  - North Africa, 1943 (Envelope G)
    Note
    For item list, see Box 1, Folder 3.
  - North Africa and Germany, 1943, 1945, undated (Envelope H)
    Includes postcards of Germany (five of Berchtesgaden).
  - Austria, Germany, Italy, primarily U.S. Signal Corps photos, 1945 April-May (Envelope I)
  - North Africa, circa 1943 (Envelope J)
    Includes 97 prints of North Africa, circa 1943; 5 prints of William P. Miller; 2 prints of William Miller with others; 3 prints of unidentified people; 4 prints of General Mark W. Clark with others, undated.
  - U.S. Signal Corps medal ceremonies and dinner, undated (Envelope K)
    Includes 10 prints of William P. Miller; 12 prints of William Miller and others; 10 prints of scenes in Germany (?); 2 prints of Brigadier General G. F. Wooley; 2 miscellaneous prints, undated.
  - Germany, 1943 (Envelope L)
    Includes 5 prints of Heinrich Himmler's summer home on the Tegern Sea, Germany; 1 print of Wernher von Braun and Megnus von Braun surrendering to American troops, Reutte, Austria, 1945; 3 prints of Brigadier General Carl A. Baehr receiving the Croix de Guerre from General Lattre de Tassigny; 1 print of Edouard Daladier and Jean Daladier; 1 print of General Maxime Weygand, Lt. General Alexander M. Patch, Jr., and General Maurice Gamelin; 1 print of Edouard Daladier, lt. General Alexander M. Patch, Jr., and Paul Reynaud; 1 print of Lt. General Alexander M. Patch, Jr. and Paul Reynaud; 1 print of Maurice Gamelin, Edouard Daladier, and Payl Reynaud; 1 print of Jefferson Coffrey and Lt. General Alexander M. Patch, Jr.; 1 print of Lt. General Alexander M. Patch, Jr. with others; 1 print of Lt. General Alexander M. Patch, Jr. and Maurice Gamelin; 65 prints of Germany, Austria, France.
  - Italy, Germany, Austria, 1945 (Envelope M)
    Includes 71 prints of Germany and Austria, 1945; 7 prints of Congressional group's visit to Germany, 1945 (prints include Rep. Edward Izac, Sen. Everett Saltonstall, Rep. Dewey Short, Rep. James W. Mott, Maj. Gen. Lowell W. Rooks, Lt. General Alexander M. Patch, Jr.); 1 print of Polish General Komoruski Bor; 1 print of François Comte de la Roque; 1 print of Maj. General Anthony M. McAuliffe and Gen. Maxime Weygand; 1 print of Gen. Komoruski Bor and others; 1 print of Maj. General Anthony M. McAuliffe and Edouard Daladier; 1 print of Paul Reynaud; 1 print of Paul Reynaud, Maj. Gen. Anthony M. McAuliffe, Gen. and Mme. Maxime Weygand, Gen. Maurice Gamelin, and Edouard Daladier; 1 print of General Komoruski Bor and others.
  - Germany and Austria, 1945 (Envelope N)
    Includes 1 print of Lt. Gen. Alexander M. Patch, Jr. and Gen. Jean de Lattre de Tassigny; 1 print of Maj. Gen. J. T. Lewis, Lt. Gen. Alexander M. Patch, and Gen. Jean de Lattre de Tassigny; 7 prints of American Ambassador to France Jefferson Coffrey's visit to Dachau, 1945; 4 prints of Under Secretary of War Robert R. Patterson, Lt. Gen. Alexander M. Patch, Jr., and Brig. Gen. Patrick H. Tansey; 1 print of Lt. Gen. Alexander M. Patch, Jr., King Leopold III of Belgium and Princess de Rethy (wife of King Leopold), and Lt. Gen. Wade Haislip; 1 print of Lt. John G. Winant (son of U.S. Ambassador to Great Britain); 1 print of Under Secretary of War Robert P. Patterson and Lt. Gen. Wade Haislip; 1 print of Under Secretary of War Robert P. Patterson, Lt. Gen. Alexander M. Patch, Jr., and Lt. Gen. Wade H. Haislip; 1 print of Maj. Gen. J. T. Lewis, Lt. Gen. Alexander M. Patch, and Gen. Jean de Lattre de Tassigny.
  - Negatives, undated (Envelope O)
  - Album, 1939-1945 (Envelope fP)
  - Soldiers and refugees in Eastern France, 1945 January- February (Box 4, Envelope 1)
  - Active combat and shots of German strongholds, 1945 January (Box 4, Envelope 2)
  - Eastern French civilians employed by U.S. Army, German occupied paper factory, and German prisoners, 1945 (Box 4, Envelope 3)
  - German prisoners, French infantry, Battle for Colmar, and liberation celebrations, 1945 February (Box 4, Envelope 4)
  - Colmar Pocket, including German roadblocks, booby trapped roads, flooded streets of Sarralbe, France, 1945 February (Box 4, Envelope 5)
  - Colmar Pocket, 1945 February (Box 4, Envelope 6)
  - Frontline investigations, Colmar liberation celebrations, and aerial views, 1945 February (Box 4, Envelope 7)
  - Front lines fighting and civilian evacuation, 1945 February (Box 4, Envelope 8)
  - Soultz, France ruins from Nazi bombing, 1945 (Box 4, Envelope 9)
  - Alsatian refugees, bridge bombing, and aerial shots of Eastern France, 1945 January (Box 4, Envelope 10)
  - Frontline activities, 1945 January-February (Box 4, Envelope 11)
    Includes 8 prints of Charles de Gaulle.
  - Military movement East, 1945 February (Box 4, Envelope 12)
  - Eastern France and Germany, including aerial shots of bombing, 1945 (Box 4, Envelope 13)
  - Panorama views of enemy-held Saar river, 1945 February 15-17 (Box 4, Envelope 14)
  - Battle of Colmar, including images of the original 1869 model statues of Statue of Liberty, 1945 February (Box 4, Envelope 15)
  - Colmar mass decoration ceremony, 1945 February (Box 4, Envelope 16)
  - German border, 1945 February (Box 5, Envelope 17)
  - Allied forces building roads, 1945 March (Box 5, Envelope 18)
  - Enemy positions, 1945 March (Box 5, Envelope 19a)
  - Forbach, France, 1945 January- March (Box 5, Envelope 19b)
    Includes prints of amphibious training, Yugoslav military, German surrender, and POW hospital escape.
  - Assault training and new construction for tank passes (Box 5, Envelope 20)
  - Battle for Uttweiler, 1945 (Box 5, Envelope 21a)
    Includes prints of Bitche, France and Eschringen, Germany.
  - Saarbrücken area, Germany, 1945 March (Box 5, Envelope 21b)
  - Infantrymen to the front, 1945 March (Box 5, Envelope 22)
  - 7th Army troops pushing through German held territory, 1945 (Box 5, Envelope 23a)
  - 7th Army reconnaissance troops and retaking German line, 1945 March (Box 5, Envelope 23b)
  - Saarbrücken, Germany, cavalry reconnaissance, 1945 March (Box 5, Envelope 24a)
  - Enemy fire and post air-raid, France and Germany, 1945 March (Box 5, Envelope 24b)
  - Infantry movements, 1945 March (Box 5, Envelope 25)
    Includes prints of freed Russian women, civil affairs authority being established, and General Alexander Patch being awarded honorary citizenship of Luneville, France.
  - Trenches, German prisoners, Rechtenbach, Germany, 1945 March (Box 5, Envelope 26a)
  - Rhine river crossing, 1945 March 29-30 (Box 5, Envelope 26b)
  - Rhine river crossing and no man’s land, 1945 March (Box 6, Envelope 27a)
  - Bombings into Aschaffenburg and German slave labor freed (Box 6, Envelope 27b)
  - Erbach, Germany, 1945 April (Box 6, Envelope 28)
    Includes prints of wounded German, French, and Polish soldiers.
  - The Landsberg atrocity and prison, 1945 May 4-5 (Box 6, Envelope 29)
  - Dachau concentration camp liberation and conditions, 1945 April-May (Box 6, Envelopes 30-32, 35)
  - German surrender (Box 6, Envelopes 33-34)
    Includes prints of German Army Group “G” unconditional surrender at Haar, Germany. The represented delegation included Lt. Jacob L. Devers, Gen. Alexander M. Patch, Lt. Gen. Wade Haislip, Major Gen. John O’Daniel, Brig. Gen. Pearson Menoher, and Edward Ott.